Piri Halasz
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Piri Halasz papers
1969-2009
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Halasz, Piri
0.8 linear feet
The papers of Piri Halasz are dated 1969-2009, and measure 0.8 linear feet. The collection consists of correspondence with Clement Greenberg and a number of well-known artists, manuscripts of articles, complete and partial drafts and transcripts of lectures and talks, interview transcripts, exhibition reviews, research, biographical material, photographs and printed material documenting her activities as an art critic, writer and curator.
Provenance
Donated 2010 by Piri Halasz.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original material requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Piri Halasz (b. 1935) is an art critic, writer, lecturer, teacher, curator and blogger who focuses on the New York art scene and politics from the 1940s to the present. She corresponded with a number of well-known artists; her long-standing association with Clement Greenberg is represented in her correspondence, articles and interviews.
Halasz, a native New Yorker, attended Barnard College where she majored in English literature. After her graduation in 1956, Halasz worked at Time magazine for six years as a researcher, primarily in business news, before being promoted to writer. For the next six years, she wrote articles covering a range of subjects including obituaries, celebrities, books, current trends and world affairs. Her 1966 cover story for Time, "Swinging London," was a cultural snapshot of mid-1960s London that resulted in an invitation to write A Swinger's Guide to London. Published by Coward McCann in 1967, it is scheduled for republication in 2010 as part of the Authors Guild "Back in Print" program.
In 1967 Halasz was assigned to write the art page of Time. Her 1969 article about Helen Frankenthaler attracted the attention of Clement Greenberg and they became close friends. Greenberg encouraged her to leave Time, which she did in 1969.
She returned to Columbia in 1974 to pursue graduate studies in art history and obtained her PhD in 1982; a substantial section of Halasz's dissertation was devoted to Greenberg's philosophy. Halasz has since pursued a career as an art critic, writer, lecturer, teacher, curator and blogger. In 1996 she launched "From the Mayor's Doorstep," an online column of art criticism and politics which became a blog in 2010.
Halasz has taught at Columbia University, Hunter College, C. W. Post Center Long Island University, Molloy College, and Bethany College. She has published articles, primarily on art, in The New York Times, Smithsonian Magazine, The Virginia Quarterly Review, Arts Magazine, Art in America, ARTnews and NYArts.
Her self-published book, A Memoir of Creativity: Abstract Painting, Politics and the Media, 1958-2008 (iUniverse, 2009), is an insider's view of the publishing industry, the New York art scene and an explication of her theory of "multi-referential imagery. This theory posits that abstract painting refers to imagery that is unconsciously significant to the artist which then triggers recognition in the viewer.
Ms. Halasz lives and works in New York City.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Piri Halasz are dated 1969-2009, and measure 0.8 linear feet. Correspondence with Clement Greenberg and a number of well-known artists, manuscripts of articles, drafts and transcripts of lectures and talks, interview transcripts, exhibition reviews, research, biographical material, photographs and printed material documenting her activities as an art critic, writer and curator.
The series titled "Greenbergiana" contains various materials related to Greenberg, including an interview Halasz conducted with Greenberg in 1991, a questionnaire filled out by artist Pat Lipsky Sutton concerning Greenberg's ideas about her work, and items concerning his death and memorial services.
Correspondence contains letters from Anthony Caro, Helen Frankenthaler, Clement Greenberg, Jules Olitski, Larry Poons, Anne Truitt, and others. There is a folder of greeting cards, some with original artwork, from artists of her acquaintance. Also found is correspondence with publishers about articles she submitted. Photographs are of Halasz and colleagues.
Writings include drafts of published and unpublished articles about Pablo Picasso, Ad Reinhardt, Abraham Rattner, Jennings Tofel, Larry Poons, Stanley William Hayter, Morris Louis, Manhattan museums, Randy Bloom and other subjects. There are transcripts of lectures and talks given by Halasz, and transcripts of interviews she conducted with Stanley William Hayter and Randy Bloom.
"A Year in the Life of Present Modernism," an exhibition curated by Halasz, was held in 1997-1998 at the Tribes Gallery, New York City. Documentation includes printed material, photographs, and biographical information about Halasz and participating artists.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 4 series:
Series 1: "Greenbergiana," 1989-1996(Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1969-2007 (Box 1; 0.2 linear ft.)
Series 3: Writings and Related Materials, 1980-2009 (Boxes 1-2; 0.6 linear ft.)
Series 4: "A Year in the Life of Present Modernism," 1996-1998 (Box 2; 1 folder)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Hayter, Stanley William, 1901-1988; Louis, Morris, 1912-1962; Picasso, Pablo, 1881-1973; Poons, Larry; Rattner, Abraham; Reinhardt, Ad, 1913-1967; Tofel, Jennings, 1891-1959
Subjects-Topical:
Art critics--New York (State)--New York; Art historians--New York (State)--New York; Authors--New York (State)--New York; Curators--New York (State--New York
Types of Materials:
Drafts (documents); Greeting cards; Interviews; Lectures; Manuscripts; Photographs; Transcripts; Writings
Names:
Caro, Anthony, 1924-; Frankenthaler, Helen, 1928-; Greenberg, Clement, 1909-1994; Lipsky, Pat, 1941-; Olitski, Jules,1922-2007; Poons, Larry; Truitt, Anne, 1921-
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- "Greenbergiana," 1989-1996, Series 1:; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  Materials relating to Greenberg consist of letters and cards concerning his death and memorial services, the transcript of an interview Halasz conducted with Greenberg in 1991, and a questionnaire about Greenburg completed by Pat Sutton. Also included are two issues of The Edmonton Review containing an interview with Greenberg and a tribute to him.
  - Materials Relating to Greenberg, 1989-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence,1969-2007, Series 2:; (Box 1; 0.2 linear ft.)
  Among the correspondence are letters and greeting cards, several from artists, including original artwork by David Edison and Francine Tint.
  - Frankenthaler, Helen, 1983-2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Greenberg, Clement, 1969-1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Greeting Cards, 1987-2007 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1983-1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Olitski, Jules, 1984-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Truitt, Anne, 1983-1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Writings and Related Materials, 1980-2009, Series 3:; (Boxes 1-2; 0.6 linear ft.)
  Included are partial drafts and final texts of articles (published and unpublished) and lectures. Also found are related materials such as correspondence about and contracts for lectures, and correspondence concerning articles not present in Halasz's papers.
  The lecture titled "1946: As it Saw Itself" is about Ad Reinhardt. Included with this text is a reworking of Ad Reinhardt's Tree of Modern Art drawing by Smithsonian Fellows to commemorate her departure. The folder titled "National Museum of American Art" contains the text of a talk about Abraham Rattner. Materials regarding "Ella Blooms at the Gershwin" include the article published in Lingo #7, a photograph and the transcript of an interview with Randy Bloom.
  - Articles, Published (Box 1)
    - "The Impact of Expressionism in N.Y. in the 1940s," 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence in response to Article on Multi-Referential Imagery, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Interview with Stanley William Hayter, and Article, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence regarding "Growing up Progressive," 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "Ella Blooms at the Gershwin," 1991-1997, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Articles, Unpublished (Box 2)
    - "Response to an Exhibition" and "A Postscript to Picasso at the MOMA," 1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "N.Y. Museum Exhibitions... Multi-Referential Imagery," 1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "Morris Louis and His Critics;" "Poons and Steiner: Growing Up; "2 Years and 3 Months," 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Book Reviews of A Memoir of Creativity, 1956-2008, by Piri Halasz, 2006-2009 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Talks (Box 2)
    - "1946: As it Saw Itself," 1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - National Museum of American Art, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Symposium on Jennings Tofel, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - CAA Talk, AICA Panel on the Education of Art Critics; Boston Museum School, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "The Current Scene and the Coverage Thereof," 1987 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "An Atypically Modernist Childhood: How Does it Play?," 1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Ad Reinhardt's Tree of Modern Art Revisited," 1998 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Last Year, This Year in the Big Apple," 1998 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "What Do They Really Want in N.Y. (Artwise, That Is?)," 2000 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "The New York Art Establishment," 2000 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- "A Year in the Life of Present Modernism," 1996-1998, Series 4:; (Box 2; 1 folder)
  This series documents an exhibition curated by Halasz at the Tribes Gallery, New York City. Among the items are promotional reviews, exhibition views and biographical materials about Halasz and the seven artists represented: Randy Bloom, Frank Bowling, John Adams Griefen, Roy Lerner, Jill Nathanson, Pat Lipsky Sutton and Francine Tint.
  - Materials Relating to Exhibition, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 15)